Well, good morning, Canvas.
Thanks so much for joining us this morning, whether you're here in person or watching
online.
We are so glad that you are here for Super Bowl Sunday.
My name is Ryan, and I have the privilege of being one of the pastors here.
And last week, we started a brand-new series through the book of James, which I am really
excited about.
We said that James is unlike a lot of the New Testament letters because it's less about
theology, it's less about explaining to believers why they should believe what they should believe,
and it's more about obedience.
It's James writing to a group of people that grew up their whole lives in the religious
system, understanding the Old Testament, and then he had some time with them after they
converted to Christianity to explain theology, and he's just more worried about them obeying
what they already know to be true.
And I think it's a really timely message for us as believers because, you know, I think it's
possible for, I think I said this last week, it's possible for Christians in America to be educated
beyond our obedience, to know a lot about the Scriptures, to believe good theology, but
not to live it out, not to love our neighbor as ourselves.
I'm really excited just to continue through the book of James.
I'm excited about this series and really specifically excited more than I normally am about our message
this morning that got his light on my heart.
I tend to be more of a teacher than a preacher, and so I tend to be a little bit more calm,
and I don't yell a lot, but I'm going to be honest with you, the end of this message
so clearly articulates the victory that we have in Jesus that I think I might yell a little bit.
And if we can't yell about Jesus, then we shouldn't be yelling about the Cincinnati Bengals, all right?
I'm just saying, I'm not a preacher, I'm a teacher, but so feel free to yell along with me
if you want to get excited.
If you're going to yell at the TV this evening, let's get pumped for the victory that Jesus has
secured us on the cross and through his resurrection.
So let me just pray one more time, and then we will hop back into James chapter 1 and see what
God has for us this morning.
Father, we are so thankful yet again for another opportunity to gather together with other believers
in Christ and other people who might be searching for answers to why they are here, to what this
whole life is all about, to why creation is so beautiful and yet so broken.
What could have happened?
Why is this all the way that it is?
And your word gives us such a clear picture that you created everything and it was good.
And that sin entered the world and sin broke in this throughout your creation.
And now your creation eagerly awaits for the second coming of Jesus when you will restore all
things and make all things good again.
And so until that day comes, God, we hold on to that truth.
We have faith in that truth.
We believe that truth, and we try to live in light of your original design.
We try and bring a light to the world.
And so, God, I pray for your Holy Spirit to just use every aspect of this service to draw us under your
truth, to believe it, but not only to believe it, to be willing to obey it even when it's difficult,
even when it's hard.
And so, God, may your Holy Spirit just be present and active today.
May we decrease and may you increase for your glory.
In Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
So, we're going to be in James 1, starting verse 12.
If you are a follow-along type person, you want to go there, it should be on the screen as well.
As we kind of hop into that, I'd love to take a quick poll.
I like to get the, I don't know if you guys notice this, but I tend to like some participation at the beginning.
And so, I'd love to have kind of a conversation about what your favorite subject was in school.
If you're watching online, feel free to hit the like button or drop in the comments below.
But if you were a science person, do me a favor, raise your hand.
We got any science nerds in here?
Wow, we got a lot of science people in here.
A lot of medical field people are in here, so that might be that.
What about math?
Anybody math person?
We got some math people in the room.
Good amount of math people.
All right, let's hear our honest people in the room.
How many of P.E. was your favorite subject?
Some of us, all right.
We got some CrossFit people that are like P.E., that's me.
Band theater, if we got any band geeks, any theater people, awesome.
What about, all right, here's the last one, and this will transition to our topic.
How many English people do we have in the room?
Oh, our front row people are English people.
So, I'm going to be honest with you.
English was and is by far my least favorite subject, and it's not even close.
I have always just been bad at English.
I blame my mom.
I was homeschooled for kindergarten and first grade.
She taught me how to read, and she taught me how to spell everything phonetically.
And so, I spell everything phonetically.
I'm really bad with the rules of grammar.
Every week when I finish my sermon, I get ready to send my slides to Dave.
It's like I have this panic attack that there's going to be some really clear, glaring, terrible grammar mistake on the slides,
and all of my English people are going to not listen to anything I say because West Virginia is on the screen clearly and boldly.
And look, some of that is my fault.
But if we can just be honest, some of that is the English language is fault.
Like, the English language sometimes can be complicated, difficult.
Not all of the rules always make sense, and sometimes they contradict themselves.
So, I might think I'm right and then realize that there's some reason why the rule changes and I'm wrong.
And I think a great example of this is homonyms.
So, a homonym is two or more words that have the same spelling or pronunciation, but they have different meanings or origins.
So, we know this, right?
Like, words that are spelled the same or sound the same that have two totally different meanings.
I have a couple examples for us.
The word rock, right?
You could say, let's listen to some rock today.
Or you could say, let's go skip a rock today.
Same word, two very different meanings.
What about the word well?
I hope you are feeling well today.
Or I hope you're feeling well enough to dig a well today.
Like, those are same words, totally different meanings.
Last example I have is the word kind.
The word kind.
So, you could say, wow, he is really kind.
Or you could say, wow, he is a real one of a kind.
And those two words can mean totally different things.
And sometimes they can even mean opposing things.
And the reason that I tie this illustration back to the book of James is because last week we talked about, James talked about trials.
And this week you're going to see your text flip and it's going to start talking about temptations.
And so, in your English translation, you're going to see two different words.
You're going to see trials at the beginning of James and temptations here picking up in verse 13.
But the reality is in the Greek, it's the same word.
They mean different things based on the context.
And so, James is going to say, hey, when trials come, you should face them with joy because trials can produce a positive outcome.
So, last week we said trials, same word as temptations in your English translation.
Trials, you should face with joy because God has a positive outcome.
He has spiritual maturity.
Like, we are conformed to the image of Jesus through our trials.
This week he's going to transition.
He's going to say the same Greek word, temptations, but he's going to say you should avoid temptations because temptations produce a negative outcome.
So, in this whole section of James chapter 1, he's talking about the same word meaning two things based on the context.
He's saying trials are a good thing.
They might not feel good in the moment, but they're good.
They produce a good outcome.
Spiritual maturity comes through trials.
And then he's going to say avoid temptation because there is a negative outcome for temptation.
And that negative outcome is disobedience that leads to destruction.
That's going to be James' whole main point for this passage from verse 12 all the way down to verse 18.
He's going to say there is a negative outcome to temptations.
And that negative outcome is disobedience that leads to destruction.
So, essentially, James' whole point from where we started last week to where we're going to end this week is that believers in Jesus, followers of Christ,
we should embrace trials with joy because we should embrace trials with joy because we know that God can produce a positive outcome from them.
But we should avoid temptations because ultimately they lead to disobedience that ultimately leads to destruction.
So, that's kind of where we're going for the rest of the day.
Now, let's read it starting in verse 12.
James says, God blesses those who patiently endure testing and temptation.
So, good things come out of enduring temptation with joy because spiritual maturity comes through it.
Afterwards, they will receive the crown of life that God has promised to those who love him.
And remember, when you are being tempted, same word, different meaning.
When you're being tempted, do not say, God is tempting me because God is never tempted to do wrong and he never tempts anyone else.
Temptation.
Temptation comes not from God but from our own desires which entice us and drag us away.
These desires give birth to sinful actions or to disobedience.
And when sinful actions or disobedience is allowed to grow, it gives birth to death and destruction.
So, believers, don't be misled.
Whatever is good and perfect is a gift coming down to us from God our Father who created all the lights in the heavens.
He never changes or casts a shifting shadow.
He chose to give birth to us by giving us the true word.
And we, out of all creation, have become his prized possession.
So, verse 12, he says, listen, the goal for believers, our goal is to finish our life faithful to God.
Like, to finish our life still following the way of Jesus.
He says, those people who patiently endure trials, who patiently endure temptation, they are blessed.
They will receive the crown of life.
And this crown of life is an illustration that they would have understood in the context of the Roman culture.
That wreath that was put on the head of a runner who finished the race.
And James is saying, listen, the goal for followers of Jesus is to finish the race.
And our lives are filled with things that will try and get us off track, try and keep us from finishing the race well.
I've recently been talking a lot about the world, the flesh, and the devil.
These are three components in this fallen, broken world that are all trying to get us to give up, trying to get us to stop running the race, to stop following Jesus.
Life gets hard.
Things get difficult.
Trials enter our lives.
And James says, no, keep persevering.
Because those who finish the race faithful, they will receive this blessing.
They will receive the crown of life.
And so this verse 12 is kind of tying the two paragraphs together, tying trials and temptation together.
He's saying, listen, you will have both trials and temptations.
And both of those things can keep you from finishing the race well.
But blessed are those who finish the race well, who endure trials and avoid temptations.
Blessed are those who persevere trials and avoid temptation.
And then he goes on in the next couple of verses and explains why is temptation bad?
How does it work?
Why is it bad?
Why does it produce a bad outcome?
He starts in verse 13 by saying, consider the source.
He says, when you are tempted, whenever you feel temptation drawing you away from God, drawing you into sin, you should know first and foremost that that temptation is not from God.
And James is later in verse 17 going to say that anything good and perfect comes from God.
So therefore, if temptation doesn't come from God, we can automatically call it out and say that temptation is not from God.
Therefore, it is not good.
It has evil intent.
We should consider the source.
Whenever we are tempted, we should be naturally skeptical of that temptation.
We should automatically say, hold on, this temptation isn't from God.
It's trying to lead me away from God.
So I should pay attention to it.
Jesus, when he's teaching believers how to pray, the famous Lord's Prayer, right?
He says, lead us not into temptation.
Jesus knows that temptation is a negative thing that produces negative outcomes.
And so he says, when we pray, we should ask God not to lead us into temptation, that we would be able to avoid temptation.
James says at the forefront of this talk on temptation to consider the source.
I don't know if you've ever been in a conversation with someone and they pointed out some strange political thing that you've never heard of before.
They're like, did you hear that, you know, the U.S. government is doing this and so we should build a bomb structure in our backyard.
Have you guys ever heard something like that?
And you're like, oh, like, send me the link.
I didn't hear that.
Send me the link.
And then they send you the link and you open it up and you're like, oh, okay, consider the source, right?
Like, there are sources on both sides of the political spectrum where you open up the link and you're like, okay, like, I can process this information, but I'm going to process it understanding that this person or this writer is coming from a certain perspective.
They have a certain bias.
So James is saying when you're tempted, consider the source, like it's not a good source.
Temptation is not a good source.
He says when trials come, consider the source as well.
Like, God can use trials to produce positive outcomes.
But when temptation comes, call it out and know that it's not from God and therefore the goal is not to produce something positive, but to produce something negative.
Ultimately, verse 15 tells us that the goal of temptation is to bring about death and destruction in our lives.
And far too often at the beginning of temptation, we play with it.
We mess around with it because at the beginning of temptation, it's not so clear that the end result, the end goal is death.
It doesn't seem like it's that big of a deal.
It's not the beginning of temptation, but at the end, we ultimately know, James is saying here, that temptation leads to destruction.
So he says, consider the source.
It's not from God.
And if it's not from God, then what is the source?
Verse 14, he says, temptation comes from our own desires.
The source of temptation is our own desires.
Some translations you have might say lust, or the idea behind it is an appetite or a thirst.
There is a desire that we have, and ultimately that desire leads us away or deceives us into searching for satisfaction in that desire that comes from something other than God.
So temptation starts with desire.
And temptation in and of itself is not a sin.
Right?
Like, I talk to a lot of believers that feel guilty about being tempted.
They feel bad.
They feel defeated.
They're like, I'm tempted to do this.
I'm tempted to do that.
I feel like I'm a bad Christian or something like that.
Temptation happens to all of us.
Temptation is not a sin.
But we pay attention to temptation because temptation can very quickly and easily lead us into sin.
So don't feel guilty about being tempted.
But when you are tempted, pay attention to that temptation and see what is it that your desires are telling you.
Ultimately, desires aren't always bad, but how we choose to satisfy those desires, determine whether or not it's sin or not.
Jeremiah 17, verse 9, again, consider the source.
The human heart is the most deceitful of all things.
It is desperately wicked.
Who really knows how bad it is?
And so when we have desires, we just have to consider the source.
We have to acknowledge that our desires are coming from within us, and within us is a heart that is deceitful and wicked, and that can lead us astray.
That can lead us down a path that does not lead to life or flourishing that God has designed.
So James says, consider the source.
It's not from God.
It's from your desires.
Again, your desires aren't always bad, but oftentimes your sinful heart tells you to satisfy those desires in a way that goes against God.
It's designed.
So there's this period of time I think we see in the text that's not really clear, but I think we can parse it out, is in between desire and disobedience is this piece that is deception.
So in between we have this desire, there's this temptation, and then before the temptation turns to sin, there's this deception where we believe a lie about the desire.
Again, because not all desires are sinful.
Desires often times have good satisfactions, good things that God designed for those desires to be satisfied with.
But between, if we're not paying attention, if we're not careful, that desire, our sinful heart can lie to us and tell us that we can fulfill that desire in a way that goes against God's design.
I love how Pastor Vance Pittman puts it.
He says,
All temptation is rooted in the lie that something other than God and his will can meet my needs and satisfy my desires.
All temptation is rooted in the lie, the deception, right?
There's a deception between our desires and our disobedience.
In the moment when we're tempted, we have to pay attention to what we're thinking about that temptation, that desire, because there are godly ways that we can satisfy that desire, and there are sinful ways.
And ultimately, the lie, the deception, that God or something other than God or his will can satisfy those desires.
That's where the sin comes into our life.
In between our desires and our disobedience is the playing ground where sin happens.
So, just to get super practical about how this works in our life, right?
Like, I got a couple illustrations I want to draw.
Number one, hungry.
Being hungry is a desire.
Is that a sinful desire that you have, like being hungry, wanting food?
That's not a sinful desire, right?
There's plenty of godly ways to satisfy the desire of being hungry.
That wouldn't be disobedient.
That wouldn't lead to death or destruction.
But eating a 12-pack of tacos and a large Baja Blast at midnight on a regular basis might be considered an unhealthy decision and not stewarding God's resources well, not stewarding the body that you've been given well.
So, there's a desire and there's good ways to fulfill that desire and unhealthy ways that ultimately, you know, you do it once or twice, not a big deal.
But you spend, those of us that have been in college who lived off of McDoubles and McChickens and combining the two at midnight might not be the healthiest way to steward the resources that God has given you.
Being angry, listen to this, being angry about an injustice at work.
You see somebody being taken advantage of.
You see somebody being used at your workplace.
Being angry about that thing and wanting to see that injustice addressed, that is a desire.
And that desire is not sinful.
That is a good, godly desire.
God wants his followers to stand up against injustice.
Standing up for justice is not a sin.
But if you allow that anger to turn into bitterness, and that bitterness drives you to gossip and slander behind other people's backs, that is disobedience.
That is where that desire for justice, and there's a righteous way to fulfill that desire.
But if you're not careful, if you let bitterness and angriness grow in your heart, you can very easily turn that desire into disobedience because you're believing a lie.
You're believing that you can satisfy that desire apart from God's will.
God's will is that justice happens.
God's will is not that you go behind people's backs in anger and slander and bitterness and gossip.
Like, there is healthy and righteous ways to address the desire, and there are unhealthy, sinful ways that ultimately lead to destruction.
Wanting to enjoy an evening of fellowship around the fire with some drinks is a desire.
But after a few, when you decide that you deserve a few more, because after all, you've worked really hard.
You've been really stressed, and you deserve an opportunity to unwind.
That desire, there's deception that is bred between desire and disobedience.
And you tell yourself that you deserve something that is outside of God's designs for your life.
The desire for sex inside of marriage is a good desire.
But when you decide, it would be easier for you to satisfy that desire behind a computer screen instead of taking time to invest in the relationship with your spouse that God has created you for.
That would lead to true, soul-satisfying intimacy, that is deception between desire and disobedience.
When you begin to believe the lie, that there are other ways to satisfy the desire outside of God's design, that's the playing ground.
When we move from just this desire, this temptation, to this disobedience.
See, there's a negative outcome to temptations.
It's disobedience that leads to destruction.
And so when we're tempted, when our desires show up, we pay attention to what we're telling ourselves about those desires.
Is there a healthy, God-honoring way to satisfy these desires?
If not, we need to pay attention to those things.
In what ways are we being drawn away, enticed out of that desire into disobedience?
The language that James uses there is actually that of like a fishing lure, right?
Like it's like this fake thing that looks real.
It's like this fake thing that looks like it's going to ultimately satisfy you, but you know deep down inside it will not.
So, James is saying temptation starts with your desire.
And if you're not careful, your desire can be lied to, to believe that there's another way to satisfy that desire outside of God's design.
And when your desire is deceived, it brings forth sin, and sin ultimately brings forth destruction.
So, I don't know if any of you Bible scholars in the room noticed this yet or not, but James is retracing the first sin.
He's retracing the experience that Adam and Eve had in the garden.
He's saying the first sin, the first temptation that led to sin, that ultimately led to destruction,
is a pattern for how every other temptation happens from the moment that Adam and Eve first sinned until the moment that Jesus returns again.
All of our temptations follow the same desire that Adam and Eve had in the garden.
See, Eve, she had a desire.
She saw that the fruit was pleasing to the eye.
And was that desire bad?
Was it bad to look upon the fruit that God had created and said,
that fruit looks beautiful, that fruit looks good?
No, that desire is not a sin.
But God had said very clearly, this one fruit, it's off limits.
Don't touch it.
Don't eat of it or you will surely die.
And so she had a desire.
The desire in and of itself wasn't bad.
But in the moment of her desire, the enemy shows up and deceives her.
He says, you won't surely die.
So in the moment between her desire and her disobedience, she's surrounded in a beautiful garden with every fruit tree you could ever imagine.
And God says, taste and eat, enjoy all of the good things except for this one fruit.
Just this one fruit.
Don't eat of it.
Trust me.
Believe me.
Because if you eat of it, it will lead to death.
Just believe that I have good plans for you, that I have a good life designed for you.
Just listen to me.
And she has this desire.
That tree looks good, though.
And then in that desire, she's deceived.
She's told a lie.
You won't surely die.
And so then Adam and Eve believe the lie that that desire could be satisfied outside of God's plan for their life.
And they disobey.
And that disobedience led to destruction.
And since that day, every temptation that we face follows that same pattern.
We have a desire.
And there's a time in between our desire and our disobedience where we can either believe God's word and find a way to satisfy the desires that honor God.
Or we can be deceived into believing that there's a better way to satisfy our desires.
That we can satisfy our desires outside of God's plan for our life.
And in between the desire and the disobedience is the ground in which we decide whether we're going to obey or disobey.
Whether we're going to believe truth or we're going to believe a lie.
So, James is saying, when desire comes about, pay attention to that desire.
Look for ways in which you can satisfy that desire in a way that honors God.
The root of every deception between our desires and our disobedience is the lie that God isn't good.
This is the lie that Satan told Adam and Eve.
And between their desire and their disobedience, he says, God is trying to steal from you.
God is trying to rob you of this good experience, of this wonderful experience.
You've had all of the fruit in the garden, but it doesn't taste near as good as this fruit.
God, he's not a good God who's given you good gifts.
He's a God that's trying to keep something from you, that's trying to take from you.
And if you really want to have your desires fulfilled, you believe that God isn't good.
This is the lie that started it all.
Adam and Eve believed that God was trying to keep something good from them.
So, James is saying here, for us, if we want to have victory over temptation,
we have to pay attention to what we believe about our desires.
Do we believe that God is good?
If so, then there is a good and righteous way to fulfill most of our desires.
And if there isn't a good and righteous way to fulfill most of our desires,
we have to call that out and believe that God has a good plan for us.
Believe that that desire isn't worth chasing after,
because if it was, God would have created a righteous way to satisfy it.
Anytime you're beginning to believe that God doesn't have your best interest in mind,
you should call that out and remind yourself of the truth that God is good
and that he has a better solution to any desire that you might have.
Best way I could think to illustrate that is magnets.
I don't know, I said, you know, science isn't my favorite,
but science costs and you get to play with magnets.
That's always fun.
So, I got this really strong magnet here.
And for those of you, anytime that you play with strong magnets, right,
like, I can keep these two objects this far apart,
and they're never going to affect one another.
Like, I don't feel any pull or any resistance or any restriction.
But there's this moment in time, right now I feel nothing, right,
but there's this very brief moment in between when this piece of metal is stuck to this piece of metal.
If I can get it off.
There's a very brief moment where you start to feel the pull.
And I can keep it here all day long.
There's no pull, there's no pull, there's no pull.
But there's a very brief moment where I can feel the pull, and I can, well, that doesn't work.
I can feel the pull, and I can still pull it away before it sticks together.
And that illustrates perfectly for us this moment in between our desires and our disobedience.
There's a moment in time where we feel the pull.
We feel the enemy, our flesh, the world, the devil lying to us and telling us,
there is a way that you can satisfy this desire that is in opposition to God's will.
And I promise you, it will feel good.
It will satisfy you.
It will reward you.
There's a moment in time where we feel the pull.
We feel ourselves being lied to.
And we have an opportunity to call that out, to acknowledge that, and say, no, that's not true.
My God is good.
My God has a good plan for my life.
He has a good design, a good will for my life.
And so when we feel that pull, the goal for us as followers of Jesus is to feel the pull and say,
I've got to get out of here.
I've got to leave this situation.
I have to believe truth in this situation because if not, we will be deceived,
and that deception will ultimately lead to our destruction.
We have a small window of time where we can acknowledge deception and can speak truth to that lie
before it draws us into disobedience that leads to destruction.
Having victory over temptation is all about what we do in that moment between our desire and our disobedience.
Will we believe a lie or will we believe the truth?
There's a perfect illustration of this in Proverbs where Solomon is talking to an unwise person in Proverbs 7.
He says, while I was at the window of my house looking through the curtain, I saw some young, naive men.
I saw one man in particular who lacked common sense.
I love how nice Solomon is.
He said, he was crossing the street near the house of an immoral woman strolling down the path by her house.
It was twilight.
It was the evening, and darkness was about to fall.
Do you guys feel this?
This young man has a desire.
And he's allowing himself to just walk down this path towards this sin that will ultimately lead to destruction.
So, he goes down to take a walk.
It's a nice night for a walk.
So, I'm going to go down to where the immoral woman is because I know where she hangs out.
I don't want to do anything with her, but it's such a nice night for a walk.
And her neighborhood is the nicest neighborhood.
So, I'm going to go to that neighborhood for a walk.
And the woman approached him seductively, dressed in sly of hearts.
He was the brash, rebellious type, never content to stay at home.
She is often in the streets and in the markets, soliciting in every corner.
She threw her arms around him and kissed him.
And with a brazen look, she said, I have made a peace offering, and I have fulfilled my vows.
You are the one I was looking for.
Deception, deception, deception.
You can be satisfied.
Your desires can be satisfied.
Don't worry about the consequences.
Don't worry about how this will affect your life.
My bed is spread with beautiful blankets, colorful sheets, Egyptian linen.
I have perfumed my bed with myrrh, aloe, cinnamon.
Come, let us drink, and let us have a fill of our love until morning.
Let us enjoy each other's caresses.
For my husband, he's not home.
He's away on a long trip.
He's not coming back for a while.
So, she seduced him with her pretty speech and enticed him away with her flattery, with her deception.
And this is a perfect illustration of what we do, how we often wrongly handle temptation.
Right?
We're like, oh, I'm just going to dabble with it.
I'm just going to hang out with it.
It's not going to cause that much problems.
I'm just going to go for a walk down by the immoral woman's house.
I'm not going to talk to her.
I won't even look at her.
I'll keep my head down.
I'll just enjoy the walk.
And then over that entire story, he had time after time after time where he could have snapped out of it and said, no, this is outside of God's design for my life.
Yes, my desires might be satisfied in the moment, but this is disobedience that's going to lead me through destruction.
And time after time, he had that window, that pocket of time where he was getting sucked in and sucked in and sucked in.
And all he had to do was snap out of it and say, no, this is against God's plan for my life.
God has a better plan for my life.
And we've all seen ourselves do this.
Time and time again, the deception starts small and it gets worse and worse.
And we justify it because we have a desire that we want to be satisfied and we don't care if it leads to disobedience.
The lies we tell ourselves in between desire and disobedience are, it's not that big of a deal.
It's not going to hurt anyone.
I've been through a lot.
I deserve this.
Does God really care about this?
No one is going to find out.
The immediate benefit far outweighs my inevitable consequences.
James is saying, follow Jesus.
Pay attention.
Sin hides its consequences.
Sin deceives you in the moment between desire and disobedience.
It's lying to you and trying to get you to believe that God does not have a good plan for your life.
And I know, I know stories in this room of people, testimonies that would say, I never intended to end up where I ended up.
I didn't think that it was going to be that big of a deal in the moment.
I didn't think that it was going to hurt anyone.
But James is saying, listen, temptation is nothing to play with.
Because temptation drags you away to disobedience.
And disobedience drags you away to destruction.
So look, I know up until this point that this is a pretty heavy message for us.
It's a pretty heavy message for me.
Because there's a lot of us in the room where we've had some big failures in our life.
Like some of you right now are thinking about times in which you allowed deception to breed lies in your life.
And you allowed your life to go down a path that you never would have intended for yourself.
And there's guilt and shame there.
And some of us, we're just in this cycle of shame where we've just failed so many times that we identify by that sin.
We're like, you know what?
I'm stuck in this pattern of sin and I'm never going to get out.
And we have shame and guilt.
But I have good news for you this morning.
See, James and all of the writers of Scripture are clear that Satan, he came to steal, kill, and destroy.
But Jesus, Jesus has come to bring life.
James is saying, how do we defeat temptation?
Look at verse 16.
He says, don't be misled.
Don't believe a lie.
Whatever is good and is perfect, it's a gift coming down to us from God the Father who created all the lights in heaven.
He never changes or casts a shifting shadow.
So he chose to give birth to us by giving us his true word and we, out of all creation, became his prized possession.
He's saying, Satan, the world, the flesh, they all have a plan for our desire.
And that plan is to lead us to a place where they can steal, kill, and destroy from our life.
But Jesus, Jesus came to give us life.
Matthew chapter 4.
James is rehearsing how the temptation worked for Adam and Eve in the garden.
And how every temptation since then works.
Desire leads to deception.
Deception leads to disobedience.
Disobedience leads to destruction.
But there was one man.
His name was Jesus.
And in Matthew chapter 4, it says this, that Jesus was led by the Spirit into the wilderness to be what?
Tempted.
Jesus was led in the wilderness to be tempted there by the devil.
For 40 days and 40 nights, Jesus fasted.
He became very hungry.
And during that time, the devil came and they said to him,
If you are the Son of God, tell these stones to become loaves of bread.
So we've got Adam and Eve in a perfect garden.
With everything going right for them.
With God providing everything that they could ever need or imagine.
And then, in that moment, there's a desire.
And Satan shows up and deceives and lies.
He seeks to steal, kill, and destroy.
And he says, God's not good.
God's trying to keep something good from you.
You won't surely die if you eat that fruit.
And they believed that lie.
Their desire.
In their desire, they were deceived.
In their deception, they sinned.
In their sin, it led to destruction.
But then, God sent his Son, Jesus.
Who in, not a garden, but in a desert.
Starving.
40 days of no food.
Hungry.
He had a desire.
Hunger.
And Satan came and said,
You can fulfill that desire apart from God's plan for your life.
Just, you're the Son of God.
Just turn that stone into bread.
And what does Jesus do?
In the moment between his desire and his disobedience, he speaks truth to it.
He says, no.
The Scriptures say, people do not live by bread alone, but by every word that comes from the mouth of God.
See, in a moment of extreme desire, Jesus was tempted to satisfy his desires apart from God.
But in that moment, in that moment where he felt the pull, the draw between his desire, he felt a draw.
He acknowledged it.
And he says, no.
No, I'm going to trust God's word.
I'm going to believe that God has a better plan for my life.
He chose to believe that God's way is better.
See, Jesus has succeeded in every way that we have failed.
See, we have all failed in this.
All of us, we've had a desire, and we've believed a lie about that desire, and we've sought to find satisfaction in our lives apart from God.
But one man entered a desert, was tempted in the same way that we were tempted.
And yet, he succeeded in every way in which we have failed.
And because of that, listen, brothers and sisters, because of that, you do not have to be perfect at defeating temptation.
Jesus did that for you.
But, you can consistently have victory over temptation because Jesus has showed you the way.
When in your desire, you're tempted to believe a lie about that desire, call it out.
Speak truth to it.
Remind yourself that God is good and that he has a good plan for your life.
See, Jesus has secured your final victory.
And he has given you the Holy Spirit to strengthen you for your current victory.
There is a negative consequence, a negative outcome to temptation if we allow ourselves to be lied to.
And if we're going to run the race faithfully, if we're going to finish our lives and receive that crown of life for finishing the race,
we're going to be a people that learn to embrace trials and avoid temptation.
We're not going to be perfect at it.
We're going to fall short day in and day out.
But Jesus was perfect for us.
He secured that victory for us.
And now he's given us the Holy Spirit, given us strength to be able to, in the moment when we are being deceived,
our desires are enticing us away into sin.
We can speak truth to ourselves in that moment.
I love how Paul says that we can take every thought captive when you're being tempted to believe that God is trying to rob you of joy.
And you remind yourself that God is good and that he has a better solution to any desire that you might have.
Jesus has secured your final victory and he's given you the Holy Spirit to empower your current victory.
What will we do with that?
Will we pay attention to our desires that are trying to deceive us into disobedience?
Will we remind ourselves that God is good, that he has a good plan for our lives?
Will we allow the enemy to lie to us over and over and over again?
One of my favorite verses in all of the Bibles, in Hebrews chapter 3, says to encourage one another daily,
so that none of you will be hardened by the deceitfulness of sin.
See, there's this thing that happens to us if we're not careful, if we don't pay attention,
that if we believe enough lies, our heart just gets hardened.
We just constantly are living underneath this deception that God isn't good and that he doesn't have a good plan for us.
And in my heart for us, it's not that we'd be perfect.
It's just that we try, that we pay attention, that we would take hold of the victory that Jesus has purchased for us on the cross,
that we would follow his example, that when, in that moment, between his desire and his disobedience,
he chose to speak truth to it.
He chose to believe that God's plan is good.
This week, when you face temptations, when your desire tells you to find satisfaction apart from God's design, God's plan,
and you're like, my prayer is that you speak truth to it.
Jesus quoted Scripture to the enemy.
He says, no.
God's way is better than your way.
Your way leads to death and destruction.
God's way leads to abundant life.
Let us be a people who, in the tension between our desire and our disobedience,
call out the lies and speak truth to it.
We obey because Jesus has purchased that victory for us.
Let me pray.
Father, I thank you for Jesus, who succeeded in every way in which we failed,
who was tempted in every way in which we were tempted.
Yet, he did not sin, and he secured for us final victory.
If we would just place our faith and trust in him, we received the victory.
May we have practical, daily victories over temptation.
May we not give in to sin that leads to destruction.
May we be a people that shine the light of Jesus.
That in our temptation, we speak truth.
We believe God is good.
We seek to find a way to satisfy our desires in a way that honors God.
For your glory and for our good.
In Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.